International Arts Society Cinema Club Records, 1953-2007
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
International Arts Society Cinema Club Records 1953-2007
MS 522
International Arts Society Cinema Club
The International Arts Society Cinema Club Records are comprised of financial, planning, and program files, programs, tickets, intermittent membership rolls, and newspaper clippings about the organization for the full span of its existence, 1953-2007. The International Arts Society was founded in 1953 at the University of Arizona in Tucson to “present mature cinema for the enjoyment and edification of University faculty, staff, and students.”
3 Linear Feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Historical Note
Arthur T. Grant, Robert Hammond, and Frank Hoskins formed the International Arts Society in 1953 to bring foreign cinema to the University of Arizona campus community. Hoskins was Professor of English and left the University in 1954. Hammond was Professor of French, and left the University in 1967. Grant was Educational Research Analyst for the University through the 1960s. Charles Scruggs joined the University of Arizona Department of English in 1967, and became director of the International Arts Society in 1971, seeing it through to its end in 2007.
In the days before personal media, cinema clubs were formed to present foreign, experimental, and avant-garde cinema to enthusiasts. Cinema clubs were often found on college campuses, where audiences were receptive to non-Hollywood film, and where foreign language students would be able to hear spoken language as well as to engage with cultural productions from around the world. From the founding of the earliest cinema club at Smith College in the 1920s through the rise of consumer-grade video, cinema clubs exposed college audiences to cinema as an art form and a window on world cultures. At many colleges in the U.S. after World War II, the cinema club introduced the community to the work of Ingmar Bergman, the French New Wave, Eastern European and Middle Eastern directors, and the national cinemas of India, Mexico, Russia/USSR, to name but a few.
At the University of Arizona, IAS members could see 10 films during the school year, shown on Fridays at 4.40 and 7.15 p.m. for an initial subscription price of three dollars per academic year. Students in foreign language courses were given free admission to the early screening. Over the years, the offerings expanded to weekly screenings, up to 14 per semester, still for less than $10 per year. Most films were shown on 16mm in the Main Auditorium (now Centennial Hall), and after 1971 in the Modern Languages auditorium, with a few on 35mm and in Cinemascope in Gallagher Theater in the Student Union. After a hiatus 1990 to 1999, the IAS returned in 2000 and finally disbanded in 2007.
In its first phase, from 1953-1969, founder A.T. Grant saw the series as an important cultural aspect of a growing university with an international community of students and scholars; late in his tenure the organization began giving small grants from its profits to support student filmmaking projects in hopes of cultivating a film program in the Fine Arts curriculum. The IAS also contributed funds to the sound system upgrade in the Main Auditorium (now Centennial Hall). In the one year during which the Student Union Activities Board (SUAB) ran the series, 1969-70, the records reflect an attitude of maintaining status quo. The 35-year tenure of English Professor Charles Scruggs included more experimental and documentary films, psychedelic program art, revival programs of Hollywood silent films, and a 1982 visit to campus of director Billy Wilder during a four-day symposium on his work. The series went on hiatus 1990-1999, and resumed from Fall 1999 to Spring 2007.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series.
Series I: History and Yearly Programming Files 1953-2007
Series II: Film Research Files 1953-1990
Scope and Content Note
The International Arts Society Cinema Club Records contains yearly records (1953-2007) of the film series, along with film ordering and rental records, intermittent membership records and program notes on each film screened. Correspondence with IAS members and with film distribution companies also appears in annual folders. Supporting files contain programs from other college cinema clubs, film notes organized alphabetically by title, and two folders of organizational history.
Scruggs, Charles.; Grant, Arthur T.; Hammond, Robert M., (Robert Morris), 1920-; International Arts Society Cinema Club.; Cinema club – U.S.; Film society – U.S. – Arizona; Tucson (Ariz.) – History.; University of Arizona – History.; Annual Membership Passes; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Printed 4-Color Film Series Programs; Financial Records; Mimeograph masters; Notebooks; Mimeographed and photocopied program Notes
Container List
- Series 1: History and Yearly Programming Files, 1953-2007
  This series is arranged chronologically. It contains annual film series brochure-calendars, viewing notes for films presented, rental records, membership lists, and correspondence with IAS members, film distributors, and other advisors to campus cinema clubs around the country.
  - IAS History, 1953-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - IAS History – Programs, 1953-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Other Film Society Programs, 1953-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Business Records, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Program Notes, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Business Records, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Program Notes, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Business Records, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Program Notes, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Business Records, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Program Notes, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Business Records, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Program Notes, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Business Records, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Program Notes, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Program and Records, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Program and Records, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Program and Records, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Program and Records, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Program Notes, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Program Notes, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Program Notes, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Program Notes, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Program Notes, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Program Notes, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Program Notes, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Program Notes, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - HIstory and Research Files, 1972-1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Program Notes, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Program Notes and Billy Wilder Film Festival, October 1982, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Program Notes and Film Research Files, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Program Notes, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Program Notes and Film Research Files, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Program Notes, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Program Notes and Business Records, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Program Notes and Business Records, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Program Notes, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Program Notes, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Program Notes, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Program Notes, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Program Notes, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Program Notes, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Program Notes, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Program Notes, 2006-2007 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series 2: Film Research Files, 1953-1990
  This series is arranged alphabetically by film title. It contains reviews, summaries, and viewing notes from a variety of campus cinema clubs, including Dartmouth, Yale, University of Hawaii, University of California at Santa Barbara, as well as film societies in New York, San Francisco, and other U.S. cities.
  - Films, A, 1953-1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Films, B, 1953-1990 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Films, C, 1953-1990 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Films, D, 1953-1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Films, E, 1953-1990 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Films, G, 1953-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Films, H, 1953-1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Films, I, J, 1953-1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Films, K, 1953-1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Films, L, 1953-1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Films, M, 1953-1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Films, N, 1953-1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Films, O, 1953-1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Films, P, Q, 1953-1990 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Films, R, 1953-1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Films, S, 1953-1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Films, T, 1953-1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Films, U, V, 1953-1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Films, W, 1953-1990 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Films, X, Y, Z, 1953-1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)